<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Eli Rodríguez Pérez</title>
    <link>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Eli Rodríguez Pérez</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 12:25:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data and conclusions on Green Blue decision making</title>
      <link>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/data-and-conclusions-on-green-blue-decision-making/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 12:25:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/data-and-conclusions-on-green-blue-decision-making/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hello GB friends, I&amp;rsquo;m Seven. I wanted to write an article on probabilities for certain decisions that are common in Green Blue. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing ramp decks (mainly DKP RB), a couple of sets, and with these kind of decks relying so much on chance to draw ramp and some key cards, I believe that is key to delegate certain decisions to probability.
I like to think about a card game as you would for a chess game for the most part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using an even smaller keyboard</title>
      <link>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/using-an-even-smaller-keyboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 15:40:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/using-an-even-smaller-keyboard/</guid>
      <description>40% ortholinear keyboard  Last time I discovered the wonderful world of QMK and keyboard firmware customization. If you remember, we went onto how important it is to feel comfortable using your keyboard, specially when it&amp;rsquo;s your work tool. I teased this post with a question that said: &amp;ldquo;could I go even smaller?&amp;rdquo;. And so, even smaller I went.
40% ortholinear keyboard   
This is my new keyboard, it&amp;rsquo;s a 40% ortholinear keyboard and it&amp;rsquo;s my new daily driver.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My current keyboard layout</title>
      <link>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/my-current-keyboard-layout/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 21:09:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/my-current-keyboard-layout/</guid>
      <description>As you may have realized based on my previous post, I&amp;rsquo;m really into improving my efficiency when it comes to programming and using the keyboard in general. That&amp;rsquo;s why I got into Vim and that&amp;rsquo;s why now I&amp;rsquo;m into keyboard stuff.
When I was little I remember my dad teaching me to touch type, we didn&amp;rsquo;t even have a computer at home, but my dad thought it was important for me to learn to use a keyboard and brought an old typewriter home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modal editing, the superior way of editing</title>
      <link>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/modal-editing-the-superior-way-of-editing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 15:29:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/posts/modal-editing-the-superior-way-of-editing/</guid>
      <description>Well ok, I might have exagerated. I actually don&amp;rsquo;t care what text editor you use, just use the one you feel most comfortable with. What I really want to transmit with this text is that there are more ways to edit text than the traditional way, the one most people use when they learn how to use a computer.
I don&amp;rsquo;t want to make anyone feel bad with this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eli-rodriguez.com/en/about/</guid>
      <description>Eli Rodríguez Pérez 
My name is Eli, I&amp;rsquo;m a programmer and a nerd. My webpage will contain articles about my personal interests and everything computers.
I&amp;rsquo;m interested in free software, emacs, vim, videogames&amp;hellip;
If you&amp;rsquo;re interested, you cand find a link to my Emacs config here. My Vim config can be found here.
You can also find me in several social networks listed below:
 https://www.instagram.com/belikeseven https://github.com/eli-rodriguezperez eli@eli-rodriguez.com  This static webpage was generated using Hugo.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>